Sapienza UniversitÓ di Roma
MSc in Engineering in Computer Science
and Artificial Intelligence
Laboratory of Advanced Programming 2025/2026
Hackathon exam - 5 March 2026
1 Mission briefing: ôWelcome to Mars. Please DonÆt Die.ö
We are in2036. After a 12-hour shift of questionable architectural decisions atSpaceY, you are
ôpromotedö toMars Operationsby being accidentally shipped to Mars while sleeping at your desk.
You wake up in a fragile habitat whose automation stack is partially destroyed. Devices speak
incompatible dialects. Some of them stream telemetry. Others respond only to polling. Actuators
are still reachable ù if you can invoke them correctly.
Your mission: rebuild adistributed automation platformcapable of ingesting heterogeneous
sensor data, normalizing it into a unified internal representation, evaluating simple automation
rules, and providing a real-time dashboard for habitat monitoring.
Failure means thermodynamic consequences.
2 General information
òDuration:5 days
òTeam size:2 to 5 students
òSubmission deadline:10 March 2026, 23:59
òFinal discussion:In-person presentation + demo (~20 minutes total per group). All mem-
bers must attend.
Suggested internal milestones:
òDay 1: short pitch + user stories draft
òDay 2: architecture defined and event schema defined
òDay 4: full end-to-end system running via docker compose
òDay 5: documentation and slides finalized
3 What you are provided with
You will receive aDocker containersimulating a heterogeneous IoT environment. Youmust
not modifythe provided container.
The simulator includes:
1. REST-based devices, which must be polled
1
2. Publish-based devices, emitting telemetry asynchronously to topics
3.1 How to run the simulator
To start the simulator, first load the image from the provided tar archive and then run the container
by publishing port 8080:
docker load -i mars-iot-simulator-oci.tar
docker run --rm -p 8080:8080 mars-iot-simulator:multiarch_v1
All endpoints are served from the base URLhttp://localhost:8080. The OpenAPI documenta-
tion is available athttp://localhost:8080/docsandhttp://localhost:8080/openapi.json.
You can also verify the simulator and list available devices using:
curl -s http://localhost:8080/health
curl -s http://localhost:8080/api/discovery | jq
3.2 REST sensors
You can list the available REST sensors by calling the sensors endpoint. The response includes the
sensor identifiers used throughout the system:
curl -s http://localhost:8080/api/sensors | jq
The table below summarizes how each REST sensor maps to its schema family:
REST sensor Schema
greenhouse_temperature rest.scalar.v1
entrance_humidity rest.scalar.v1
co2_hall rest.scalar.v1
hydroponic_ph rest.chemistry.v1
water_tank_level rest.level.v1
corridor_pressure rest.scalar.v1
air_quality_pm25 rest.particulate.v1
air_quality_voc rest.chemistry.v1
Exact definitions are provided inSCHEMA_CONTRACT.mdand via OpenAPI.
3.3 Telemetry (stream)
Telemetry topics are discoverable via the topics endpoint:
curl -s http://localhost:8080/api/telemetry/topics | jq
2
Streams can be consumed either via SSE (server sent events) or WebSocket. Use the following
endpoints to subscribe to a topic:
GET /api/telemetry/stream/{topic}
WS /api/telemetry/ws?topic={topic}
The following table maps each topic to its schema family:
Topic Schema
mars/telemetry/solar_array topic.power.v1
mars/telemetry/radiation topic.environment.v1
mars/telemetry/life_support topic.environment.v1
mars/telemetry/thermal_loop topic.thermal_loop.v1
mars/telemetry/power_bus topic.power.v1
mars/telemetry/power_consumption topic.power.v1
mars/telemetry/airlock topic.airlock.v1
Default publish interval: 5 seconds.
3.4 Actuator APIs
Actuator state can be inspected via the actuators endpoint:
curl -s http://localhost:8080/api/actuators | jq
To change a state, POST a JSON payload to the actuator resource, for example:
curl -X POST http://localhost:8080/api/actuators/cooling_fan \
-H ÆContent-Type: application/jsonÆ \
-d Æ{"state":"ON"}Æ
Available actuators include:
òcooling_fan
òentrance_humidifier
òhall_ventilation
òhabitat_heater
Actuators are controlled exclusively via REST.
4 What you must deliver
You must design and implement a distributed automation platform that:
3
1. Collects data from simulated devices (polling and/or stream depending on team size)
2. Normalizes heterogeneous payloads into astandard internal event format. You need to
define and document such a standard, and provide a file namedinput.mdas support for your
solution.
3. Uses anevent-driven architectureinternally (message broker required)
4. Evaluatessimple event-triggered automation rules
5. Maintains and exposes thelatest stateof each sensor (in-memory caching)
6. Provides a real-time dashboard. You must provide the user stories ininput.md.
4.1 Persistence
òHistorical sensor data persistence isnotrequired.
òThe latest state per sensor may be cached in memory.
òAutomation rulesmustbe persisted, so that they survive service restarts.
Rule persistence can be implemented using any kind of relational database (e.g., Postgres), noSQL
database (e.g., MongoDB), or embedded database (e.g., SQLite). Complex schema design is not
required; a simple rule table/schema is sufficient.
4.2 Authentication
Authentication isnot required. There are no user accounts. The platform may be treated as
single-tenant. All sensors are globally visible: there is no concept of ownership or association.
5 Functional requirements
5.1 Device ingestion and normalization
The system must:
òIngest device data
òConvert incoming data into a unified internal event schema
5.2 Automation engine
The automation engine must supportsimple ifûthen rules.
IF <sensor_name> <operator> <value> [unit]
THEN set <actuator_name> to ON | OFF
Supported operators:<, <=, =, >, >=.
Example:IF greenhouse_temperature > 28░C THEN set cooling_fan to ON
4
Rules must:
òBe evaluated dynamically on event arrival
òBe persisted
òTrigger an actuator state update when condition is met
5.3 Frontend dashboard
The frontend must provide a real-time monitoring dashboard. A widget-based layoutmaybe used,
but it is not mandatory: static dashboards are also acceptable.
Optional widget approach
òWidgets can be configurable (select sensor binding).
òExample widget types include live value, line chart (updates while the page is open), actuator
toggle, or custom visualizations by data type.
The frontend must also provide a rule management interface and real-time updates via WebSocket
or SSE.
6 Architectural constraints
Mandatory
òUse at least one message broker, e.g., ActiveMQ, Kafka, etc.
òUse multiple backend services (avoid a single monolithic service)
òSeparate ingestion, processing, and presentation
òPersist automation rules
òProvide architecture diagrams
Strongly discouraged:Tight coupling between services
7 Technical requirements
7.1 Tech stack
òBackend: any language/framework
òMessaging: ActiveMQ, Kafka, equivalent
òDatabase: any relational, noSQL or embedded
òFrontend: any framework/library
5
7.2 Containerization
You must provide:
òA Dockerfile per service
òA singledocker-compose.ymlthat starts backend services, message broker, frontend and
simulator container.
The system must start withdocker compose up. No manual setup after startup.
7.3 Baseline
All groups are expected to meet the following baseline requirements:
1. Event-driven architecture
2. Meaningful broker usage
3. Unified event schema
4. In-memory latest sensor state
5. Persistent rule storage
6. Real-time dashboard
7. Docker reproducibility
7.4 Tasks by group size
Groups of 5 are expected to deliver the full system and implement about 25 user stories.
Groups of 4 are expected to deliver the full system and implement about 20 user stories.
Groups of 3 are expected to deliver the full system and implement about 15 user stories.
Groups of 2 may omit telemetry stream handling (REST polling only) and implement about 10
user stories.
Note: user stories must be documented ininput.md.
8 Deliverables
Submit a public GitHub repository containing:
òFull source code
òDockerfiles,docker-compose.yml
òinput.md
òStudent_doc.md
òArchitecture diagrams
òUser stories + LoFi mockups
òPresentation slides
6
The repository must have the following structure:
.
input.md
Student_doc.md
source/
booklets/
All the textual documents must follow the Markdown syntax. Please refer tohttps://www.
markdownguide.org/basic-syntax/if you are not entirely familiar with it.
Following is the list of textual files to be submitted:
òinput.mddescribes the system overview, the user stories, the standard event schema and
the rule model. A (partial) example is accessible athttps://drive.google.com/file/d/
1klvQ8r8WKfW86HS8HQ801QZh-yXZ05sK/view?usp=sharing.
òStudent_doc.md, which contains the specifics of the deployed system. Structure
of the file:https://drive.google.com/file/d/1stCQoen6ojT3hBexAkyp0Ja8H6XzOuFn/
view?usp=sharing. An example is accessible athttps://drive.google.com/file/d/
15lmOqwYTG4qORk3bZgwMlRBWLaA5Gn-I/view?usp=sharing.
Thebookletsfolder contains whatever document you consider appropriate (slides, images, etc.).
Thesourcefolder contains the system developed in whatever technologies/framework you may
want. In this folder all the source code, configuration files, and any other file you may need (please
remember we have adopted an IaC approach - Infrastructure as Code) AND the Dockerfiles, docker-
compose files, etc. which will allow the instructors to re-build/re-deploy your system on whatever
platform (either on-premise or on cloud).
Each group needs to create a repo named<MATRICOLA>_<PROJECT>where<MATRICOLA>is the
INFOSTUD Student ID of the group leader and<PROJECT>is the acronym of your project/group.
In order to avoid misunderstandings, this is repeated. Before the discussion, you need to share
with the instructor all the documents and materials of your project, in particular the requirements
(as user stories) of your entire system. User stories can be documented by using a spreadsheet
and collecting all of them in a booklet. For each user story, it should be provided also a LoFi
mockup, to be prepared with whatever tool (e.g., Balsamiq, Figma, etc.), and a textual description
highlighting specific non functional requirements (if any).
The system is developed in whatever technologies/framework you may want. The release should be
done by providing the link of a GitHub repo with all the source code, configuration files, any other
file you may need (please remember we have adopted a IaC approach - Infrastructure as Code)
AND the Dockerfiles, docker-compose files, etc. which will allow the instructors to re-build/re-
deploy your system on whatever platform (either on-premise or on cloud).
7
